[Uhtred] My name is Uhtred,
son of Uhtred.
Born a Saxon,
but raised as a Dane.
I now serve
King Alfred of Wessex.
I have married
a pious wife for Alfred.
I have taken on land, burdened
with debt and cheating workers.
And I killed
the mighty sword Dane, Ubba.
[screaming]
But with Odda the Elder
wounded in battle,
his son took the credit for my kill.
The truth was ignored.
I fought Ubba, man-on-man,
and I killed him!
And I was forced to my knees
before Alfred's God.
I will lead but you owe me!
You must lay flat
and kiss the cross.
Kiss my arse.
Fate is testing me.
But I will survive.
[grunts]
Uhtred!
[stabbing sound]
[Uhtred] Destiny is all.
[chickens clucking]
[Leofric] You're certain you
want to do this, arseling?
Is there a law against it?
Dressing up as Danes, no;
plundering Cornwalum, yes,
we're supposed to be at peace.
[Uhtred] If I'm to reclaim
Bebbanburg, I'll need an army!
If I am ever to raise an army,
I'll need silver. We go.
I have no quarrel.
Will Odda not miss you?
I'm doing as he asks,
I'm watching you.
He's building Alfred a church,
at Cynuit; have you heard?
With an altar of gold they say.
-Who are they?
-They belong to Oswald.
Their mother sends them,
hoping to shame me for killing
their lying, thieving father.
[kid grunts]
I see her plan is working.
They're not the first
to lose a parent.
They'll live.
[fire cackles]
[belches]
The food is good, Mildrith.
Thank you.
I'm pleased you like it.
I was beginning to believe
you had lost your tongue, wife.
I was worried.
I doubt it.
She grieves for the thief.
Not my business.
He kills a man
I have known all my life;
he refuses to pay wergild to a
family I have known all my life,
and the village my father helped build
now call him, "Uhtred the Godless."
Not forgetting that I refuse to
have my son baptized a Christian.
-I will excuse myself.
-Leofric sit, please.
-None of this is my business.
-I'll stop.
Tomorrow I'll be gone.
-[Mildrith] Gone?
-Should anyone ask,
we are keeping Alfred's kingdom
safe... again.
For how long will you be gone,
and gone where?
-No idea how long... weeks.
-Your place is here.
Oswald's wife has gone
to the Bishop Alewold.
The bishop will go to Alfred,
and Alfred will send
men to our door.
I won't pay a penny,
and if men do come calling,
that's what you will tell them.
He was killed because he was
a thief, that's my law.
Leave me and I'll go
directly to the church
-and have our son blessed.
-Then he won't be my son.
May God forgive you
for saying such a thing.
-Which God?
-What has happened to you!
What has happened to the
kindness, and perhaps even
the love you have once shown me?
-I was made to crawl!
-Yes, before God!
We all fall
to our knees before God.
I won't forget what Alfred did
to me in the name of his God.
I reject that God!
I will excuse myself.
Are you there still?
The man I cared for?
Are you there still,
the woman I ached to plough?
[Odda the Younger] Progress
has been made daily, Lord.
You must come to Cynuit
and inspect the building work.
Oh, I will, I will.
I would like that.
It's impressive enough,
even now.
Yes, we have the nave here...
-Mm-hmm.
-...the transept thus,
and then into the chancel.
With its already famous
altar of solid gold.
It will be gilding, no more, Lord,
but you know how tongues wag.
-Mmm.
-With your permission,
I would like to place
the altar just here.
Why would you need
my permission?
It's on the exact spot where
Ubba Lothbrokson is now buried.
You wish God's altar
to be built over
the buried remains of a Pagan?
Oh, no. No, Lord.
With your permission,
we will exhume the remains,
and I don't know,
have them thrown into the river.
You will exhume the remains
and have them buried elsewhere,
unmarked, but with respect.
It was a joke Lord;
a poor joke.
We must do nothing
to endanger the peace.
With respect, Lord,
I am not the fool
my father at times
made me out to be...
Father Beocca,
you wish to see me?
Ah, a letter, Lord,
from Bishop Alewold.
-Private or business.
-A matter of law, I was told.
Then read it.
Let Odda's active mind rest.
Well, can you not read
the writing, Beocca?
It concerns
the Aelderman Uhtred.
He has slain a farm-worker
and is refusing to pay
the monies owed
to the family, the wergild.
Would you like me
to investigate further, Lord?
No, no,
it is not your place.
Odda, you shall investigate the rights
and wrongs of the matter on my behalf.
I only hope for the sake of Uhtred's
wife, the killing was justified.
Uhtred has always been
fair-minded;
I am sure
there are mitigations.
Mmm! We shall see.
In the meantime, Odda, do you
your best, keep the peace.
Yes, Lord.
Father Beocca, the letter.
You might do well to examine
your loyalties, Father.
My loyalties are to God
and to the king, in that order.
Lord are you suggesting
I am wrong?
I am suggesting nothing of
the sort, but I am watching you.
And God is watching all of us.
Uhtred!
I'll find the wealth
to pay off the debt.
We want the same thing,
the land of our birth.
Yours won't be taken from you.
Mine?
Are you no longer the Aelderman?
I'll never be accepted
as an Aelderman; not here.
Then I beg you for one last time,
change your ways, Uhtred.
If you allow God into your heart
he will guide you!
I can never become
the man you want me to be.
-You could try.
-I would despise that man.
[Leofric] Arseling!
[baby coos]
I have loved you.
Don't pray for me.
Did you hump her
goodbye, arseling?
I want to have
left Wessex by tonight.
You're gonna have to ride
faster than that, arseling.
Yah!
[horse whinnies]
No one is to wear these til
we have crossed into Cornwalum.
What you can do is polish them,
so that when we do wear them,
they will be seen, clearly.
And you'll be feared.
You're going to find out
what it's like to be a Dane.
Every man stand where he is!
No one move!
You! Stay where you are!
Do I know you?
Lower your hood.
I said lower your hood!
Aethelwold!
[stutters]
I merely want to come with you,
to be part of your adventure.
I wanted it to be a surprise!
-[chuckles]
-He cannot be here,
he cannot hold his tongue.
I say we kill him.
Kill me?!
You can't kill me.
I'm the rightful king, you fool.
Not here! Leofric!
Not in Wessex!
Then I will drag him
into Cornwalum!
-Not now!
-You... you can't!
Uhtred, you owe me a favor.
I call it in now!
If Alfred hears of Christians
raiding Cornwalum
we will all be killed!
He guarantees that outcome!
Leofric, I am a changed man!
I swear.
We kill him.
He will not be missed.
We take him with us.
I owe him.
He's my responsibility.
He has my protection.
And who will protect
the rest of us?
I've never seen him so angry.
You will clean our mail
and tend to the horses.
Anything.
You will wipe
our arses if I say so.
Of course. I am gathering the moss
and dock leaves as you speak, Lord.
What do you know of Cornwalum?
That it is not Wessex.
The Wessex/Cornwalum border
is this river, the Tamar River.
Which is why we are camped here.
It flows North to South.
And Cornwalum itself,
has a coastline
shaped like a leg.
So they are traders?
Yes, on the North Coast to the
Welsh Kingdoms and Ireland,
and on South to the Franks.
How do you know this?
I am an educated man, Leofric,
I simply enjoy hiding the fact.
You do it well.
[chuckles]
Do they have a king?
[Aethelwold] More than one.
Fierce fighters?
Have no fear Leofric,
we are Danes.
[chuckles]
I want to be blooded in battle.
[chuckles] Don't worry, boy,
you'll be first in line.
I look forward to it.
[chickens clucking]
[woman]
Good day, Lord.
Tell your master,
Aelderman, Odda is here,
-with God's Bishop Alewold.
-Yes, Lord.
Quickly!
It is not the most desirable
farmstead I have seen.
Aelderman Odda, Bishop Alewold,
a pleasant surprise.
May I offer a refreshment?
We are here
in the king's business.
Tis with your husband...
Is he here?
He is not.
Can he be fetched, my dear?
All crucifixes and crosses!
You are God fearing Christians,
no more.
You are Danes now, Pagans.
You don't cross yourself
nor look to the heavens.
[chuckles]
Let's make ourselves rich!
[all cheering]
[Mildrith] My husband
is protecting our kingdom
From whom, we are at peace?
He only said he was doing
Alfred's work.
He doesn't trust the Danes.
He thinks he
knows better than the king.
Your own man, Leofric,
will give you detail, I'm sure.
Yes.
Odda, it's not the child's fault
that she was married off
to a tyrant and a fool.
No... Of course not.
Mildrith,
it is with great reluctance
that I must serve you
with this letter.
For your husband,
upon his return.
He must settle the wergild
for Oswald's death
or face confiscation
of his property.
Which is also my property.
If you are ever in need,
my fathers' house
will always be your house.
How is Lord Odda faring?
Well, I hope.
Frail. He's still very frail...
...the blow would have
killed many a man.
Take consolation, lady, that
should your land be confiscated,
it is the church
that will benefit.
[screaming]
[yelling]
Where's it buried?
Where's the silver?
Where is it?
These people have nothing.
[man] Please...
[grunts]
Five days and nothing...
There is time yet.
We are not the first Danes
they have seen. I need silver.
So we keep looking.
And what if the whole of Cornwalum
has been sacked already?
We keep looking.
We keep heading west.
Do they want to speak?
Five men, to match theirs.
Only I speak... Aethelwold?
I heard:
Only the Great Uhtred speaks.
I am Brother Asser.
I bring you a gift,
from my king.
From King Peredur.
King who?
King Peredur, of the Britons.
Never heard of him.
[Asser] I assure you
my king as heard of you.
A troop of Danes raiding villages
in Cornwalum does not go unnoticed
Why does your Peredur send me
these miserable offerings?
[Asser]
A gesture of peace, a token.
Our King has been attacked
by a fellow Briton and neighbor,
Callyn, whose forces have seized
the fort guarding our land,
I am sent to tell you, Peredur will pay
you well to help recapture this fort.
Pay us well? How much?
I do not know the sum but I am
sure he will be generous
He has silver?
He is a king...
[children playing]
[grunting]
Winchester, it is not.
Alfred, he is not.
The king greets you.
He does? I hear nothing.
You are Pagans,
the king is Christian,
and will only
speak with you through me.
If you would come forward
and pay your respects.
Please inform the king:
Danes do not bow to Christians.
This fort
you want us to recapture,
it's defended
by how many Britons?
And what price will you pay?
[indistinct whispering]
It would be much simpler if
the king addressed me directly.
Easy...
They have between
40 and 50 men; no more than 50.
We are 30, fighting men.
And we are 20.
How much in silver?
One hundred pieces of silver.
I won't bargain.
I'll tell you the price.
-Four hundred pieces of silver.
-That is an absurd sum.
[Uhtred]
Is Peredur a king or not?
I will call for Queen Iseult.
Lord, perhaps, instead,
you should take a moment
-and pray for guidance--
-Iseult!
You are needed!
I am blessed with two wives;
two queens.
Iseult is a shadow queen.
You know what I require of you,
of course you do.
Who are you...
...and what will
you do for the king?
I am Uhtred Ragnarnson.
I am here
to fight for your king...
...if he pays me what I'm worth.
He is the one.
You are fortunate
to have such a wife.
She is not to hump.
She is too valuable.
Four hundred...
pieces of silver...
...agreed.
[Uhtred]
I'll see it?
You will see it,
once the fort is taken.
No, I'll see it now.
All of my wealth
is hidden within the fort.
-Then your enemy has it.
-Well hidden.
You have your price,
you have my terms.
I know you'll accept;
I know
you can smell the silver.
Danes...
You have a nose
for blood and silver,
and women...
And so I will add
to the price my Queen...
...this Queen.
[laughing]
[all laughing]
If we win back the fort and you
are lying about the silver,
-I'll kill you.
-Which is why I do not lie!
Call the men up, we stay here!
I'll dream about
that shadow queen.
You told her your name,
and word travels.
[Asser]
Uhtred Ragnarson!
I have noticed that you have
Saxons amongst your ranks.
Some, from Mercia.
They'd rather fight than work in
the fields. The pay is better.
He would like to attack
at the earliest opportunity.
Does not wish to feed you
for more than one night.
How Christian of him.
He would like to be
a man of God,
but as you have witnessed,
he cannot let go
of his Pagan ways.
The Queen Iseult.
She is a gwrach.
A sorceress.
What are her powers?
Peredur believes
she can see into the future,
for as long as
she remains a virgin.
And what do you believe?
I know the devil exists.
Hiding within beauty is a trick
he will use often, I'm sure.
Tell the king
to have his men ready.
Peredur, any in the fort who
try to escape are yours, yes?
[Peredur] You will do your part,
Dane, I will do mine!
Walk on. Advance.
[horse whinnies]
Let's scare the shit
out of these bastard Britons,
see if they have
the stomach for this.
Hold...
We hold here.
Why would they leave
a fortress to face us?
Aethelwold. Advance.
Go on the ridge and see why they
are prepared to leave the fortress.
On my own?
You wanted to be
first in line.
-[horse whinnies]
-[men laugh]
What do you see?
They are Danes!
Real Danes!
Stand still! Hold!
[Peredur]
What are you waiting for?
[Uhtred]
They're Danes!
What do you care?
You people will fight anyone
for money, even yourselves.
You lied to me!
Think of the silver! The queen
has seen your victory, so fight!
Uhtred...
He's a sword Dane, a Lord of War.
If the Lord of War wants to talk,
may I suggest we listen.
Name yourself.
I am Uhtred Ragnarson.
Who are you?
Skorpa, of the White Horse.
You are the Uhtred Ragnarson
who was at Cynuit?
I am.
The Saxon son of Earl Ragnar?
Yes.
You will not defeat me,
you know this.
Perhaps not, but I could
kill half your men trying.
Oh...
Yes... Yes, you could.
Then it would be best for us
both if you did not try.
Lord, Lord I fear
what will happen
if they are allowed to speak.
Then go to them;
listen to what they are saying.
My presence, Lord would serve
only to antagonize the Dane.
Uhtred Ragnarson!
What is happening here?!
They must leave
my kingdom or die!
Bastard Danes!
The queen saw victory.
I pray, Lord.
What is your battle price?
Silver, that he says
is hidden in the fortress.
[scoffs]
[laughing]
No, no we have ripped
the fortress apart;
we found nothing.
He must have something...
Somewhere.
[Peredur] Uhtred Ragnarson!
Whatever he has, I say we split.
Half and half.
We kill his men,
we spare the king,
he takes us to his wealth.
Half and half?
I will advance;
you will turn
and we will attack together.
Now, this is for the benefit
of the king.
-You bastard piece of rassragr!
-I will destroy you!
Be ready! We kill them all,
every last one of them dies!
Tell the men
we are with the Danes.
At the ready!
You trust this Skorpa?
We have no choice
but to trust him.
[all shouting]
Now turn!
To the death!
Bastard Danes,
you'll cry for
your stinking whore mothers!
[all shouting]
[horse whinnies]
[grunting]
[screams in pain]
You lying, thieving,
bastard Danes.
I could kill
at least one more of you.
It is over.
Your wealth...
My wealth for my life is it?
Your wealth
and your shadow queen.
Useless bitch,
she saw victory.
[Skorpa]
Where is the silver?
If I tell you, you'll kill me.
And I would rather
you remained poor.
You have my word, as a warlord,
you will be spared.
Where is the silver?
Speak or you will die.
It is buried... in the hall,
beneath my throne.
I'll need
a small amount my--
[groans in pain]
[indistinct yelling]
Do we split her, too?
You have the tits,
I'll have the arse.
She's mine.
You are here for the silver.
It is beneath this seat.
I have a question.
Have you been waiting for us?
For you.
Then you saw what would happen?
I knew that you would come...
...that is all.
Uhtred, what do you know of
a church with a golden altar?
At Cynuit... To celebrate
the killing of Ubba,
I hear they're
building a church.
Who's been telling you this?
Men, begging to live.
Would say anything.
And that's where you will go,
to Cynuit?
Well, I have ships to repair,
the coastline here
has been murderous.
How do we do this?
How do we share?
We don't... share...
Oh, we can fight
and some of us will die,
including your queen.
Uhtred Ragnarson,
keep your sword in its scabbard.
Wise queen.
She stays with me.
-She stays with me!
-Do nothing!
[laughing]
[whispering indistinct]
Uhtred, no!
-Uhtred!
-They have our treasure!
No! I will not fight these Danes
for silver; for king, yes,
-but not for silver!
-I am tethered by debts!
I need to raise an army
and they get away further
with every second!
I will not allow half
of these men or more die!
I can give you what you need.
There is more... silver.
[chickens clucking]
[chuckles]
What did he whisper, Skorpa,
when he was leaving?
I will tell you when
I believe you need to know.
How was I, as a warrior?
Aethelwold, you are as much
a warrior as you are a king.
This isn't
part of the plunder.
It's a holy cross;
it goes back to the church.
There'll be blessings.
But the rest...
it's all ours!
Home?
Wessex, and our separate ways.
There is a bishop I must see.
[children playing]
[chickens clucking]
[sheep bleating]
[Iseult] I've never seen
a village like this before.
We will be here
for just the day.
Who are you?
I'll speak
with the Bishop Alewold.
Bishop Alewold is at prayer.
He'll see me...
He is at prayer
and won't be disturbed!
Alewold! Bishop Alewold!
What is this? Get out.
Out! We're busy with our work.
So I see.
I said get out!
[chuckles]
I know you...
Uhtred...
The Godless, yes...
And my wife, through her father,
has inherited a debt
to the church.
Oh, yes.
A substantial debt, I recall.
-Which I would now discharge.
-You would?
Very well, as you see
we're busy with...
[gasps]
That's Irish work.
It looks Irish.
And its weight!
A thing of beauty
and of great value.
It seemed a fitting way
of settling the debt.
If you'll accept, of course. If not,
I'll put it in the Smith's fire.
I accept. On behalf
of the church, I accept.
I trust I can rely upon your
good judgment in dismissing
the matter of my servant
Oswald's wergild.
He was a thief.
His family will
swear otherwise.
My people will swear he was.
And time will
be wasted with no end.
In that case,
consider all matters resolved.
Bless you.
[cows mooing]
[sheep bleating]
I've been praying daily
for your safe return.
Who's this?
She is a queen.
Queen of where; of whom?
Britons.
Uhtred you walked
by your son without a look.
Is he baptized now?
[Mildrith] Yes.
Against my wishes.
I have done nothing
that requires forgiveness.
[door closes]
-What's her name?
-I am called Iseult.
I am speaking with my husband,
you can kindly remain silent.
Mildrith we are hungry,
thirsty and in need of rest.
[scoffs]
I am not your servant;
do not speak to me
as if I were.
I am your wife.
You are no longer
a part of Uhtred's path.
It is true.
Out. Out!
This "queen"
can sleep with the animals.
You should know
that your land is safe.
I have seen Bishop Alewold
the debt's settled, all of it.
That's what I've come
to tell you, nothing more.
And what of Oswald's wergild?
That too is settled. His
family won't receive a penny.
Then you can explain
that to the king's council,
Alfred has called you
to the Witan.
It's finished! Everything.
Before I left I said that
I've loved you, and it's true.
You will not speak of us
in this way,
and in the presence
of a Pagan whore!
She's with me!
Will you be resting with your
family or with the animals?
[sheep bleating]
You chose the company of pigs and
a goat over your wife and son.
My wife's a good woman.
She loves her God,
and it is hard for her
to be with the like of me.
[soft chuckle]
And if the marriage
is to be ended,
I must become
used to life without my son.
I am here because I choose you.
Though I won't keep you
against your will.
What?
I will be with you, Uhtred,
from now until the very end.
That is what I see.
I want you to see my home;
my land in the north.
It is this Alfred
who directs you, for them.
You must give in to fate;
attend his Witan.
Will you sleep alongside me
tonight, under the furs?
-Sleep?
-Nothing more.
I would like that...
...as the only other source
of warmth would be the goat.
[chuckles]
[giggling]
Edwina.
Lady?
Please inform your family that
I will be traveling;
with the child.
We will leave
for Lord Odda's estate.
I would like you with me,
but it is your decision.
I know how important it is to be
amongst the people who care for you.
I would not wish to leave you.
[sniffles]
The very day I am told
that my home is my own,
is the day I decide
I must leave.
[indistinct chatter]
O Lord, grant wisdom to your
servants gathered here.
Help them to decide
what is right,
what is just and what is fair.
Grant us this, O lord.
[all] Grant us, O Lord.
[indistinct whispering]
[man]
Leave your sword.
Uhtred!
-Beocca.
-Quickly...
You're late,
you were sent for days ago,
you should have
been here on time!
Since when has my presence
been so important?
-Who's is she?
-She's with me.
Was she part of your plunder?
What's been said?
You will hear it
all soon enough.
Now, we must go and you must be
respectful, now more than ever.
And as local thegns skimp in
their duty to repair the bridges,
I wish to ask of the king
to appoint an official
to survey the kingdom's roads.
The bridge on the road out
of Avingdon, for example,
is in such a state
of disrepair...
[whispers]
Now's the time, my Lord.
it is now dangerous
for man or...
What reason do I have to
beg for mercy; what's been said?
-Quiet now.
-Is it Cornwalum?
Respect.
...remains disinterested...
We shall talk of bridges later.
Beocca, what is this?
[Odda the Younger]
You will be quiet there!
Face your king!
Come.
There is an urgent matter which,
with the Witan's permission,
we shall deal with now.
Aelderman Uhtred,
also known in your parish
as Uhtred the Godless,
you are on this day charged with
taking a troop of the king's men
into Cornwalum and there
making war against the Britons
without your king's consent.
You are also charged with joining
forces with the Dane called Skorpa,
to murder Christian-folk
in Cornwalum,
despite these folk all living in
peace with Alfred and with Wessex.
All this is proven with oaths.
And the punishment
for these crimes is death.
Who swears these oaths?
-We shall get to that.
-Show me. Who swears?
I, Brother Asser,
swear these oaths.
Uhtred, to your knees.
Never!
Lord, we were patrolling
your borders
and protecting your kingdom,
nothing more.
There is more
to my story, Lord, if I may.
Now is the time to beg.
Yes, let him speak,
let us hear his story.
On my way to make this
complaint to King Alfred,
I came via Cynuit.
And such a sight
I hope never to see again.
For, where the church to
commemorate Lord Odda's victory
over Ubba was to be built,
I saw devastation, destruction,
and the charred remains
of 15 monks or more.
Men have told me,
that this evil was the work
of the very same Skorpa
who was in Cornwalum,
and that with him, once more,
was the Aelderman Uhtred.
-No!
-This man!
No, no these are lies, Lord!
Lord, e lies with every breath!
Lord, hear me, let me speak,
and hear the truth!
We are the Witan and we shall
behave in the way of a Witan.
The Aelderman
is entitled to respond.
[Uhtred]
Yes, I was at Cynuit.
I was at Cynuit
once and once only.
I was at Cynuit on the day that I,
Uhtred of Bebbanburg,
killed Ubba.
I look around this hall
and into the eyes of the warriors
who know this to be true.
And that is the only
occasion I was at Cynuit.
We are here...
We are here to
deliver judgment on the murder
of King Peredur and the
Christian Britons of Cornwalum.
Then if I can speak
of Cornwalum, Lord?
There is a further witness,
I believe.
What if Peredur's Queen
was to stand in front
of this Witan and tell you that
Peredur lied and cheated us?
She is a shadow queen
and a Pagan Lord,
her words would be meaningless.
Is the truth
not important, Lord? Lord!
Odda, we shall move on,
there is a further witness.
Yes, Lord.
Bring the prisoner.
[crowd murmurs]
What is this?
-Odda means for you to die, as a traitor.
-You will stand separate.
And you will die.
If it is Valhalla you want,
I will do my best to give it.
I said you will stand separate!
Leofric,
you have sworn your oath.
-And you will tell the truth?
-I will, Lord.
God is merciful.
You are a man of Wessex
and have been loyal to the king?
I am loyal to the king, Lord,
always.
Where you in Cornwalum
with the Aelderman Uhtred?
I was.
Did you kill and plunder
Peredur and his Britons?
I did.
Leofric, have you now donated
your share of the plunder
to the church?
I have, Lord,
and have begged forgiveness.
The Witan hears you, Leofric.
Whom did you follow into battle?
I went willingly, Lord.
No, Uhtred led, you followed.
He is the Aelderman,
and he is to blame.
-I share the blame, Lord.
-No, he is responsible!
Irresponsible.
And he will pay
for it with his life!
For the very last time, beg.
No, I will not beg!
I will fall
to my knees for no man,
no king and no Christian God.
[grunts]
He must pay, with his life.
Lord, if I may make a plea
to the king and the Witan.
I have not yet finished.
I beg your pardon Lord,
but if I may?
It is clear that, like me,
the arseling here is guilty.
Thank you, my friend.
[choking]
It is also clear that he is too
proud and too stupid to repent,
and as a consequence, will die.
He will die for leading men
to treachery.
Because of my own guilt;
and because of my respect
for Uhtred as a warrior,
I request that he dies
at my sword.
You wish to become
executioner, Leofric?
My plea is for a fight
to the death, Lord:
me against the arseling.
If God is with me,
I will be the victor,
and the Aelderman is allowed
to die as a warrior should.
And if he wins this fight
to the death, what then?
He will not.
It would take God's intervention
for him to beat me.
Let them fight, Lord!
Let God decide!
[crowd murmurs]
Lord. Lord, it is clear
that the guilt lies with Uhtred.
Leofric, you have spoken well.
And your request is granted.
[gasps]
You will fight, tomorrow,
to the death.
[crowd cheering]
Swords and shields.
God shall determine the victor.